A Guide to Materials on Women
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Correspondence written to members of the Birckhead family 1839-1891, ca. 15 items.
  Interesting set of unrelated letters including a letter, October 30, 1859, from M. L. Moore to "Dear Sally Ann" discussing deaths in the family, with an interesting note about a lady preacher, in a letter, March 3, 1861. M. Taliafera to "Dear Sister," vehemently denies she will marry a man named Binks. There are two very interesting letters written by a former slave to her mistress. In the letter dated March 31, 1871, she relates her life to her former mistress, she is not well, misses everyone and inquires of how her mistress is doing. The second letter is a very revealing letter on several accounts. Her husband has left her to marry another woman: "[He] married a woman with two children, nearly white. I never did anything to make him leave me...He swore to every one that he was not married to me, but he just staid with me I am nearly crazy...if you have my license I would like for you to send me it, so I can prove we are married...Henry (the man in question) has not a friend in the community, black or white, every one said it was the best thing that I ...of such a trifling darkey." #1492
- Come to me only in thy bras 1948, 3 items.
  Risque poem, comments and newspaper clipping all concerning the proper fit of the bra. #3050
- Material left in library books including correspondence, notes, greeting cards, and newspaper clippings 1840-1939
  An unusual collection of items that were found in books in Alderman Library. There are items referring to women and correspondence. #86
- Marriage Bonds of Amelia, Cumberland, and Prince Edward Counties 1749-1857, 5 items.
  A collection of typewritten marriage bonds arranged by the man's surname. #38-570
- Helen McIntire Marshall Papers 1923, 1 volume
  Scrapbook of copies of letters (typescripts) February 2-November 21, 1918, written by Helen McIntire Marshall (1879-1950) from Paris while AEF/YMCA Paris office personnel secretary. Mrs. Marshall describes her voyage over on the S. S. Chicago, her life in Paris, her friends and fellow YMCA workers. Of interest are her descriptions of the German bombardments of Paris, March-July 1918, including the Good Friday bombing of St. Gervais, work with refugees and wounded soldiers, a holiday in Amboise, a trip to the front including Chateau-Thierry and Belleau Woods, celebrations on July 4th, and the Armistice. There are also her original discharge papers, letters of recommendation, photographs including Woodrow Wilson in Paris, and clippings as well as the Armistice issue of the "Paris-midi," November 11, 1918. #3533
- Garrett W. Martin Papers 1813-1935, ca. 1000 items.
  Contains receipts and correspondence of Sally F. Martin, Fannie Lee Martin Harris (1902-1935). #2883-a
- Samuel W. Marvin Collection 1879-1917, ca. 60 items.
  Correspondence addressed to Samuel W. Marvin, an executive officer of Charles Scribner's & Sons. Included are letters from the following: Maria Rebecca Audobon, Mary (Mapes) Dodge, Abby (Sage) Richardson, Edith Wharton, and Kate Douglas Wiggin. #773
- Sarah Mytton Maury 1843, 10 items.
  Subjects from the designs of the Carracci executed by Sarah Mytton Maury. #1674
- Ann Maury Collection 1790's-1850's
  Cards of pencils drawings, engravings and prints collected by Ann Maury while she lived in Liverpool, England. Prints include Fashionable Head Dresses of 1789, frontispiece for the Ladies Daily Companion for the year 1810, and An interesting scene from Coelebs in search of a wife. #1783-a
- Maury Family Papers 1807-1872, 17 items.
  One recipe book, and 16 letters. On December 3, 1834, Ann Maury writes to her Uncle Reuben requesting hams be sent and of a brother (?) who suffers from mental illness. #16
- Maury Family Papers 1720-1855, ca. 1500 items.
  Collection consists of photocopies as the originals were returned to their owner and since sold or otherwise dispersed. Items of interest are Ann Maury's diary (1827-1832), her scrapbook, and voluminous correspondence with Ruston and Matthew Fontaine Maury. #949
- Mrs. Albert Maverick Collection 1920-1950, 2 boxes.
  Short stories, poems and photographs. #1946
- Ellen Lee Mayo Letter 1904, 1 item.
  Letter, July 27, 1904, Mayo, Warrenton, writes to Mrs. M. V. S. Wylie, Winchester, to thank her for a letter of encouragement. She speaks of her desire to have Robert Mayo called to the church and mentions that Mrs. Wylie's landlady might help. #9048
- James Rogers McConnell Memorial Collections 1915-1916, ca. 100 items.
  James Rogers McConnell, a University of Virginia student who joined the Lafayette Escadrille in France during World War I. He was shot down March 19, 1917. His letters to Marcelle Guerin de Precourt, a French woman who had resided in the States in her youth and was serving as a nurse in the Ambulance Corps, provide insight into the war and their relationship. Marcelle would eventually marry twice, but many believe McConnell was the romance of her life. Also included is a brief autobiography of Marcelle Guerin. #2104
- McDowell-Miller-Warner Papers 1700-1876, ca. 600 items.
  Correspondence of Governor James McDowell of Virginia with his daughter, Sally Campbell Preston McDowell. Material relates to social life in Washington, D. C. and to Sally McDowell's marriage to Governor Francis Thomas of Maryland. (2969)
  An addition to the papers consist primarily of the letters of Sally to her second husband John Miller during the period, 1854-1856, of their courtship and marriage. Sally had divorced Francis Thomas in 1846. A strong collection concerning divorce in 19th century Virginia. Included in this collection is a ledger containing transcripts of letters from Elizabeth Jacquelin[e] (Ambler) Brent Carrington (b. 1765) to Ann (Ambler) Fisher which contain some recollections of her life as a young girl during the war. The transcripts are in a volume entitled, Illustrative Cases in Real Property. #2969, -a
- McEwen-Coleman-Twigg-Houston Family Papers 1814-1945, ca. 300 items.
  The papers of the McEwen family of Tennessee, primarily the correspondence of Hetty Montgomery Kennedy McEwen and her husband, Robert Houston McEwen (Sam Houston's cousin). In a letter dated September 1, 1814, William Kennedy to his sister Hetty, he addresses her desire to come stay near him at a Washington College (in East Tennessee), so that she could be under the direction of a certain lady from whom she might "receive instructions for improvement in life." However her brother informs her that the particular lady in question doesn't have a proper education (no French or German languages) and his sister knows more. A passionate letter to a Margaretta McEwen from a possible rejected suitor. December 10, 1833; his name has been cut from the letter. There are numerous letters of both Robert and Hetty to their children, a composition book, 1855, and travel journal of Great Britain, 1859, kept by Hetty. Also included in the collection is the journal of Mrs. James Lindsay Coleman of Bedford Plantation, Georgia, containing receipts, an account of a trip to England during the 1850's and the births and ages of slaves are recorded. #1794
- McGill-Mahone Papers 1771-1919, 5600 items.
  Papers, primarily financial, relating to the McGill and Mahone families of Petersburg, Virginia. Items of interest include the account, check and bank books of Mrs. Helen McGill (1900-1912), contract, 1812, for the sale of Negro woman and two children, the sale of Negro woman and 6 children (March 14, 1825), correspondence between William Mahone and Mrs. McGill (1892), and Mr. Mahone's letters to his wife (1893-1894). #1627.
- Julia McGruder Letter 1896, 1 item.
  Julia McGruder to Mr. Hopkins, February 20, 1896, will "comply with your request to the best of my ability, and enclose you a little paper, which you may use as you think proper." #942
- McKennie Papers 1793-1860, 21 items.
  Papers pertaining to the family of Clement P. McKennie, publisher of the Charlottesville Central Gazette. Includes letters to Mrs. McKennie from Willia S. Woods, Mary Ann Harper of London, England, and L. Wood, and between Marcellus McKennie, son of the publisher, and Miss Mary Cummings of Holly Springs, Mississippi. Microfilm 222; (#2246)
- McKennie Cookbook 1820's, 1 volume
  Manuscript cookbook of Mrs. Clement P. McKennie, wife of the Charlottesville printer and publisher of the Central Gazette, 140 pages. #2691
- McLaughlin-Redd Papers [177-]-1867, 17 items.
  Papers relating to the McLaughlin, Redd, Coleman and Minor families of Caroline County, Virginia. Of special interest is the will, June 24, 1834, of Lucy Coleman and letters, 1821-1822, between Mary O. McLaughlin and her daughter, Cornelia McLaughlin while she is always at school. #38-470
- Almira Cox McPherson Papers, 2 items.
  Collection consists of a newsclipping re the history of the Woman's Christian Temperance Union in Loudoun County, Virginia. #3332.
- Meade-Funsten Papers 1792-1906, ca. 400 items.
  Correspondence and business letters of the Clarke County, Virginia families. Included is a legal deposition relating to a slave woman and child. #3039
- Meek Family Papers 1916-1940, ca. 380 items.
  Most of the material pertains to Ada Cordelia Meek of Middlebrook, Augusta County, Virginia. Letters refer to genealogy, mission work, the Presbyterian Church, and her small mail order nursery business. Also included is an autograph album, 1856-1887 of, Isabelle Meek, and a diary and personal account book, 1861-1867. #500-a
- Septimia Randolph Meikleham Papers ca. 1700-1870, ca. 60 items.
  Personal and family letters of a granddaughter of Thomas Jefferson. Included is a letter, August 28, 1825, from a slave, John Hemmings, to Septimia. #4726-a
- Septimia Randolph Meikleham Letters 1882-1886, 42 items.
  Letters to William Erigena Robinson, a New York congressman, discuss his efforts to secure a pension for Septimia Randolph Meikleham. Other topics include plans to remove the remains of Thomas Jefferson to a more suitable location, the health of Robinson, news of family and friends, a recommendation for her nephew Hore Browse Trist, politics, and her own ill health. There is also a postcard from Meikleham to a Mrs. Colburn concerning Robinson's health. #7907-a
- Meikleham Family Papers ca. 1790-1915, ca. 100 items.
  Personal papers of David Scott Meikleham and his wife Septimia Randolph. #6065
- Lizzie B. Miller Papers 1887-1890, 1 ledger
  Accounts concerning Lizzie Miller's farm near Elkton, Rockingham County, Virginia. #38-677
- Louisa H. A. Minor Diary 1855-1866, 1 item.
  A member of the Minor family, Albemarle County, Virginia. The diary contains a weekly account of the activities of Minor, her friends and family including church services attended, with the text for each sermon, visits and visitors, family and neighborhood news, weather and social events, She quotes poetry and occasionally composes her own, and there is also a lengthy list of her reading. Most Civil War news is indirect but she does describe cooking for Ewell's troops when they came through the county and entertaining the general in her parlor. She describes the difficulties of the first year of Reconstruction and expresses her bewilderment over the insubordination and disloyalty of family servants. Microfilmed as part of the Records of the Ante-Bellum Southern Plantations, Series E, Part II, Reed 26. #10685
- Mary Berkeley Minor n.d., 1 item.
  One typescript volume of the memoirs of Mary Berkeley (Minor) Blackford (1802-1896). #2976
- Mary Willis Minor ca. 1887, 1 item.
  A manuscript by Mary Willis Minor entitled Liddy, a 39-page account of a black female child. #38-277-b
- Minor Family Papers 1838-1944, ca. 200 items.
  Business and personal papers of Launcelot Minor and his family of "Pedlar Mills," Amherst County, Virginia. Included is a daguerreotype of a female slave. #6055
- Minor Family Papers 1826-1892, 50 items.
  Primarily the papers of John B. Minor of the University of Virginia, includes a journal of Susan Colton Minor regarding a European trip, July 29-October 1, 1892. #3114-b
- Minor-Wilson Family Papers 1800-1936, ca. 25,000 items.
  Primarily the papers of John Minor (1813-1895), a professor of Law at the University of Virginia and his family. There is much correspondence pertaining to his daughters, Susan Colston, Martha, and Mary. Susan Colston married John Wilson and several of their courtship letters can be found in the collection. Martha and Mary each married and some of their correspondence is represented in the collection. #3750, 38-602
- Minnie Garnett Mitchell 1878-1879, 8 items.
  Eight school copy books concerning penmanship, lectures, songs, elocution, and dictation. #1915
- Minnie Garnett Mitchell 1888-1889, 2 items.
  Letters, November 27, 1888 and April 17, 1889, from Minnie Garnett Mitchell to her aunt Mary Evelina Dandridge Hunter from Lisbon, telling her of all the social events she attends. Evidently Minnie's father was in the embassy at Lisbon, Portugal. #1962
- Virginia Moore Poetry 1945, 11 items.
  Nine poems by Virginia Moore, plus two photos. #2152
- Anna Maria Jackson de Camp Morris 1850-1857, 1 item.
  Diary of Anna Maria De Camp Morris written on the Santa Fe Trail. #3448
- Morris Family Papers 1819-1820's, ca. 600 items.
  Family papers, mostly business or financial, of the Morris family of Hanover and Louisa counties, Virginia. Of the few personal family letters, Julia M. Watson Morris, Kate Anderson Watson, and Ann Maury are all correspondents. #38-79
- Nelson and Page Family Papers ca. 1750-1910, ca. 18 items.
  Miscellaneous papers of the Kinloch and Nelson families. Of note is the estate, 1836, of Hugh Nelson of Albemarle County, Virginia, listing his numerous slaves. #2831
- George Neville-Nellie Newman Collection 1859-1865, ca. 150 items.
  Nellie Newman, evidently the belle of the Isle of Wight, Virginia, received many love letters from different men. But it appeared that her heart belonged to George Neville. At first their relationship was jovial, with her teasing him about other women, but with the coming of the War, their relationship took a serious turn, and toward the end of the War, Christmas 1864, they were married. The letters are from George to Nellie. This is a first-rate collection in regards to the Civil War and how it affected men and women. Evidently George Neville was a high-ranking clerk and his letters are full of information regarding the War around Richmond, especially the last desperate days. Some highlights of the collection include a letter, January 28, 1858, from Nellie's cousin, A. F. Culpepper to Nellie, discussing his latest child and blaming women for so many children. A "contract," April 5, 1859, between George Neville and Nellie Newman, since she lost a bet and could not come up with $500,000, she "herein resign, give, and yield myself unto the said George S. Neville, to have, hold, use and enjoy my body, as may best suit his pleasure." A letter dated August 19, 1859, from Hannah to Nellie, describes teaching and her social life. A letter, February 8, 1864, George to Nellie, describes a lady acquaintance who had married a Yankee because at the age of 28 she was tired of waiting. A letter dated October 20, 1864, George to Nellie, indicates that they are sending every man possible to the army, and that the men in his office do not know what will happen with them. A letter containing a call by top Confederate officials to give arms to "negroes" and have them in the army. #2024
- New Providence Church Ladies Benevolent Society 1932, 1 item.
  History of Ladies Benevolent Society of New Providence Church, Lexington, Virginia, 1819-1919. #38-557
- Leigh Gibson Newell Papers 1902-1920, 225 items.
  The papers consist chiefly of letters from Newell, a University of Virginia college and law student, to his mother. He discusses his activities at the University, including a co-ordinate college for women. #10607
- Jefferson Davis Norris Papers 1860-1940, 15 boxes.
  Norris, a Maryland lawyer who received his degree from the University of Virginia in 1890 includes much correspondence with his mother, Ellen Norris, and his sisters Sarita and Susan, as well as his wife, Martha Cabell Norris and daughters Josephine and Martha. An interesting set of letters are from Ellen Norris who wrote her parents from Richmond apparently during Grant's siege. Also in the collection are the papers of George Gardner Hobson and his wife, and the papers of the Della Torre Family. Of particular interest are the letters Frank Della Torre wrote his mother during the 1870's while attending the University of Virginia. #2454
- Nourse Family Papers 1751-1918, ca. 2000 items.
  Contains a nineteenth century copy of a letter, March 10, 1782, from Mrs. Elizabeth Fouace to William Nourse, Correspondence between Joseph Nourse and Maria Nourse in the 1780's contain occasional mention of social activities in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, attended by various members of government. a microfilm copy of a transcript of a "memoir" of the Nourse family contains references to the activities of family members during the revolution. Microfilm 547; (#3490-a)
- Louise Oates Papers 1944-1945, 24 items.
  Letters, 1944-1945, from nurses in the armed forces to Miss Louise Oates. Microfilm 212; (#2348).
- Jean (Carter) and Jesse Switzer Ogden Papers 1946, ca. 6 items.
  Manuscript, galley proof, and other papers pertaining to "Small Communities in Action; stories of citizen programs at work" by the Ogdens. #3562
- Page-Walker Papers 1742-1886, 265 items.
  Primarily the papers of Thomas Walker and his son, Francis Walker. Two items of note are "A course of polite literature for a young lady," 1830, and a letter, June 23, 1852, from Judith Page Rives to Mrs. J. F. Page, chiefly family news from Paris, but she does mention Uncle Tom's Cabin. #1098
- Palmore Family Papers 1781-1958, 2200 items.
  Chiefly the correspondence and business and legal papers of the Palmore family of Cumberland County, Virginia, and their relations. Most of the correspondence is that of Joseph S. Palmore (1805-1846) and his wife, Lucy Ann (Allen) Palmore Gauldin (1807-1881), who married Josiah Gauldin in 1859. Individuals represented in correspondence and business papers include: James D. Allen (1788-1836). Sarah Palmore (d. 1834), and Lucy A. Palmore Gauldin. Substantial correspondence between the women in the family. #38-149, -a
- John Crafford Parker Papers 1874-1936, ca. 3500 items.
  Papers of John Crafford Parker of Southampton County, Virginia, primarily consisting of papers generated by his law practice. There are several cases involving women such as divorce, guardianship of children and contesting wills. Major files of legal records pertain to Sallie Darden, Bessie Leigh, Martha J. Newman, Sallie Hayes and Nannie J. Thomas. #2885,-a
- Payne Family Papers 1849-1862, ca. 60 items.
  Personal correspondence of Bettie V. (Jones) Payne and William J. Payne of Fluvanna County, Virginia. Included is a letter of November 23, 1853, from James M. Payne in Arkansas to his brother William mentioning that he had recently purchased a woman as a slave, but that she had run away the next day. #10530
- Mary Payne Letter 1856, 1 item.
  Mrs. Mary M. Payne to her father, "from a few miles beyond Wytheville." Mary and her husband were heading toward Abingdon to look for a farm to rent. Mary comments on family matters and the countryside of western Virginia. #38-681
- Paxton Family Papers 1836-1918, 50 items.
  Principally correspondence and family papers of the A. M. Paxton family of Lexington, Virginia, later Vicksburg, Mississippi. Some scattered correspondence among the women. Microfilm 26; (#38-328).
- Pendleton Family Papers 1830-1929, 1000 items.
  Primarily the financial and legal papers of Dr. Eugene B. Pendleton. There are also some legal and financial papers of his mother-in-law, Bettie Pendleton and his daughter, Anne Meredith Pendleton. #415
- Pendleton and Meade Family Papers 1826-1843, 5 items.
  Five letters from Hampton, Ameilia and Petersburg, Virginia, primarily from Mary N. Pendleton, Mary S. and Mrs. William C. Meade to their children. Mary Pendleton writes to her son in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania on the death of a member of the family. An interesting fragment appears to be from a young bride writing to her father. There are also three letters from Mrs. Meade to her children who were staying with their aunt as Mrs. Meade was ill. #38-127
- Persinger and Staples Family Papers 1793-1937, ca. 300 items.
  The correspondence includes these three groups: letters between Daniel de Jarnette Staples and Mary (Waugh) Staples (1879-1897) have the dominant theme of their enduring love and the elaborate preparations for their 1880 wedding; the letters between David W. Persinger and his Mother, Mrs. M. E. Martin (1893-1896) are concerned with his educational life in regards to his grades and progress at the University of Virginia; and than correspondence between the Persinger and Staples families cover a variety of topics. Also included is a bankbook of Mary Staples as well as insurance policies and deeds. #1000
- Joanna Person Letter ca. 1798-1801, August 26
  Letter to James Madison reflecting on her life. #38-631
- Mary Elizabeth Phillips Letter 1927, 1 item
  Letter, January 7, 1927, from Phillips (1857- ), Boston, Massachusetts, to Lewis M. Thompson, commenting on forged Poe portraits and sending a copy of her book as thanks for his help in writing it. #3565-c
- Piedmont Female Institute Papers 1860, 1917-1935, 2 items.
  A bound volume of notes from meetings, 1917-1935, of the Piedmont Alumnae Association and a report card for Miss Birtha Rives, 1860. The school was founded in Charlottesville, Virginia, in 1853 until 1905 when it became known as the Rawlings Institute and in 1910, St. Anne's School. #38-684
- John and Matthew Pilson Papers 1790-1880's, ca. 1500 items.
  Financial, business and personal papers of Matthew and John Pilson of Augusta and Albemarle counties, Virginia. Some correspondence from or concerning women. #1326, 2852, 3095
- Pittsylvania Ladies' Soldiers' Aid Society 1861, 1 item.
  A printed newspaper clipping containing a letter of October 21, 1861. Chatham, Virginia, from the Pittsylvania Ladies' Soldiers' Aid Society to the justice of Pittsylvania County, Virginia, in which they describe the aims and activities of their society and ask the justices to appropriate a sum to pay the Society's debts. #38-252.
- W. S. Plummer Address 1858, 1 item.
  A newspaper clipping of Dr. W. S. Plummer's address On the Education of Youth. Dr. Plummer believed: "Nothing has retarded the civilization of the race so much as limited and deficient female education," but he also believed "young ladies learn early that a woman's strength is, first, her spotless chasity." Dr. Plummer advocated that women should be taught to spell before anything else and not to read too many novels as young ladies begin to identify with the heroine. #155
- John Henry Ingram's Poe Collection 1829-1915, ca. 1,000 items.